National Women's Health Network records SSC.MS.00360
Sophia Smith Collection
National Women's Health Network records
1963-2011
Sophia Smith Collection
National Women's Health Network
SSC.MS.00360
254 boxes (112.41 linear feet)
Non-profit women's health advocacy organization focusing on the diversity of women's experiences; advocating women's self-determination in all aspects of their reproductive and sexual health; establishing universal health care that meets the needs of diverse women; monitoring the actions of federal regulatory and funding agencies, industry, and health care professions; providing women with objective health information from a feminist viewpoint; and supporting grassroots action. The records document activities, programs, and projects over a thirty year period.
Conditions Governing Access
The Records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the following exceptions: researchers are required to sign a Records Access Agreement agreeing not to identify NWHN program participants who are still living without their written permissions and a portion of the Depo-Provera registry in Series VIII is closed until 2065.
Accruals
Periodic additions to this collection are expected and may not be reflected in this record.
Accruals
This collection is comprised of the following accessions, some of which may not have accession records. Accession numbers: 87S-54, 87S-59, 88S-29, 94S-46, 96S-47, 97S-5, 99S-33, 02S-55, 04S-21, 07S-04, 09S-14, 14S-33, 16S-04, 16S-29, 16S-66, 2017S-016. Accessions were received on the following dates: 1987, 1988, 1994, 1996, 1997, 2002, 2004-04-13, 2007-01-18, 2009-02-02, 2014-06-02, 2016-01-12, 2016-04-05, 2016-07-05, 2017-03-02, 2019-S-0005.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The National Women's Health Network began donating their Records to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1987. Additions to the collection are expected.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into fifteen series:
I. HISTORY AND ORGANIZATION (1977-2006)
II. ADMINISTRATION (1976-2004)
III. COMMITTEES (1978-2004
IV. PERSONNEL AND BOARD MEMBERS (1979-2007
V. MEMBERSHIP AND FINANCIAL MATERIALS (1977-2006)
VI. PUBLICATIONS AND REPORTS (1976-2005)
VII. CORRESPONDENCE (1977-2006)
VIII. CONFERENCES AND MEETINGS (1977-2011)
IX. PROJECTS, PROGRAMS, AND REFORM EFFORTS (1963-2007)
X. COURT CASES AND LEGISLATION
XI. OUTREACH AND PUBLIC RELATIONS (1977-2005)
XII. AFFILIATES (1978-88)
XIII. ORGANIZATION FILES (1978-2005)
XIV. SUBJECTS AND REFERENCE FILES (1972-2002)
XV. PHOTOGRAPHS AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS (1981-2002)
Biographical / Historical
The National Women's Health Network is a non-profit women's health advocacy organization. It's goals include creating a health care public policy that reflects and responds to the diversity of women's experiences; advocating women's self-determination in all aspects of their reproductive and sexual health; establishing universal health care that meets the needs of diverse women; monitoring the actions of federal regulatory and funding agencies, industry, and health care professions; providing women with objective health information from a feminist viewpoint; and supporting grassroots action.
Created at the height of second wave feminism, the National Women's Health Network was an outgrowth of informal groups of women sharing their experiences. It was founded in 1975 by Barbara Seamon, Alice Wolfson, Belita Cowan, Mary Howell, and Phyllis Chesler as a lobby group for women's health advocacy and quickly expanded to become a clearinghouse for women's health information. It began as the Women's Health Lobby, later called the National Women's Health Lobby Network, and finally the National Women's Health Network. Since its beginnings, the Network has waged numerous legal battles and organized public education campaigns to increase women's input into the U.S. health care system. These include the first Diethylstilbestrol (DES) class action lawsuit on behalf of DES daughters, class action lawsuits against A.H. Robbins manufacturer of the contraceptive intrauterine device, Dalkon Shield, and against the Upjohn Pharmaceutical Company on the use of the contraceptive Depo-Provera. In addition the Network organized a Citizen's Petition to the FDA requesting that the Dalkon Shield be declared a banned product. The Network successfully persuaded the Federal Drug Administration (FDA) to require studies on the safety of breast implants and to establish mandatory standards on absorbency labeling for tampons to reduce preventable cases of toxic shock syndrome. It also exposed the scientific inadequacies in the clinical trials of tamoxifen. Its information packets and publications provide information to millions of women on a wide range of topics. The Black Women's Health Project (now the Black Women's Health Imperative) was originally a project of the NWHN. It also continues to assist and support local activists in their efforts to expose environmental and occupational health problems, support reproductive rights for all and the health needs of midlife and elderly women.
Currently, the Network is headquartered in Washington, D.C., with affiliates in New Mexico and New Jersey. It has 11,000 (as of December 2011) individual members.
Additional information can be found on the organization's website: http://nwhn.org/
Related Materials
Additional records can be found in the papers of Katsi Cook and Loretta Ross and the records of the Black Women's Health Imperative. In addition there is information about the Network in the Voices of Feminism Oral History Project in the interviews with Katsi Cook and Loretta Ross.
Scope and Contents
The National Women's Health Network Records consist of 103.25 linear feet, dating from 1963-2011, with the bulk of the records dating from 1976-2000. There is historical and organizational material, but the most of the records document the activities, programs, and projects over a thirty year period. Types of material include correspondence; memoranda; records of the Committees, Board of Directors and Executive Committee; annual reports; material from conferences and meetings; funding proposals, Senate and House testimonies, legal documents and court cases; financial records; program descriptions and reports, publications and articles, research papers; files of affiliated organizations; printed materials; photographs and audiovisual materials. These records provide a rich source of information on the battle for quality health care for women and reflect the NWHN as advocate, information provider, and front line activist organization. Of particular interest are files on breast cancer and tamoxifen, Depo-Provera, reproductive rights and abortion, Dalkon Shield, and consumer protection and the related legal and legislative campaigns. Documents related to the Network's class action suits against A.H. Robins and Upjohn regarding the Dalkon Shield and Depo-Provera are of particular interest, as are those related to tamoxifen clinical trials. Materials related to key subject areas can be found throughout the records and researchers are encouraged to look at all the series for topics of interest.
Abortion -- United States -- History -- Sources; African American women -- Health and hygiene; AIDS (disease) -- Education; Breast -- Cancer -- History -- Sources; Contraceptives -- Law and legislation; Diethylstilbestrol -- Law and legislation -- United States -- History -- Sources; Eating disorders -- United States -- History -- Sources; HIV Infections -- Education; Medroxyprogesterone; Menopause -- Treatment -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Oral contraceptives -- Side effects -- History -- Sources; Prenatal care -- United States--History--Sources; Public health -- United States -- History -- Sources; Reproductive rights -- United States -- History -- Sources; Safe sex; Toxic Shock Syndrome -- United States -- History -- Sources; Women -- Health and hygiene -- United States; Women's health services -- United States; Publications; Grant proposals; Mailing lists; Organization files; Minutes; Trial proceedings; Research; Videotapes; Audiotapes; Computer media; Reproductive health--United States--History--Sources; Health care reform--History--Sources; Memorandums; Women's health services--United States; Women--Health and hygiene--United States; Health education of women--United States--History--Sources; African American women--Health and hygiene; articles; Annual reports; Financial records; National Women's Health Network; Herbert, Sonja; Pearson, Cindy; Thomas, Beverly
- SERIES I. HISTORY AND ORGANIZATION, 1977-2006
  Scope and Contents
  This series documents the founding, early planning, and history of NWHN. It is arranged alphabetically and contains annual reports (including notes and background materials), articles and printed materials, Articles of Incorporation, IRS documents, and by-laws. In addition there are lists of NWHN historical highlights and achievements and progress reports. Of particular interest is "A Historical Look at the Network" by Doris Haire. There is information regarding a possible merger with other activist organizations in 1989, mission statements, and organizational descriptions. Two essays are of interest: Cynthia Pearson's "National Women's Health Network and the U.S. FDA: Two Decades of Activism" and a case study by Stephanie Burkhalter, "A National Women's Organization's Attempt to Diversify its Agenda Through Diversification of its Board of Directors: The National Women's Health Network." In addition there is an organizational issues questionnaire, policy statements, an organization profile, program planning materials, and proposals. The Network had three anniversary celebrations. Materials related to the 20th anniversary conference are located in SERIES VII. CONFERENCES AND MEETINGS, but there is documentation in this series for the 25th and 30th anniversaries. For the latter the Network honored thirty women's health activists. There is material related to the thirty honorees as well as those who were nominated but not chosen.
  - Annual reports, 1977-2006 (Box 1, Folder 1-8)
  - Articles, 1979-99 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Articles of Incorporation and IRS materials, 1976, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - By-law committee notes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - By-laws, 1980-95, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Case statement, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Highlights, achievements, progress reports, and timelines, 1975-2001, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - "A Historical Look at the Network" by Doris Haire, 1980-89 (Box 2, Folder 3-7)
  - History (miscellaneous material), 1980, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Introduction to the NWHN," n.d. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Merger discussion, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Mission statement and organization description, 1995, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "National Women's Health Network and the U.S. FDA: Two Decades of Activism" by Cynthia Pearson, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "A National Women's Organization's Attempt to Diversify Its Agenda Through Diversification of Its Board of Directors: The National Women's Health Network: A Case Study" by Stephanie Burkhalter, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Organizational issues questionnaire, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Policy statements, 1976-79 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Profile for Women's Issues Interest Group, 1990-91 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Program planning, proposals, and lists, 1980-2003, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Twentieth anniversary conference (Women's Health Summit)
    General
    [see SERIES VIII. CONFERENCES AND MEETINGS]
  - Twenty-fifth anniversary, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Thirtieth anniversary
    - Honor 30 for 30th honorees
      - Chosen, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
      - Miscellaneous related material, 1999-2005 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Not chosen, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 2-6)
- SERIES II. ADMINISTRATION, 1976-2004
  This series is arranged alphabetically and contains information regarding the two oversight units of the Network (the Board of Directors and the Executive Committee) along with contracts, legal materials, leases, and office business. According to the bylaws of the NWHN the Board of Directors is the working unit of the Network. Representing the membership, it sets policy based on priorities and guidelines determined by the Membership. The Executive Committee, which is elected by the Board is responsible for conducting business on behalf of the Board in between its meetings. The Board of Directors subseries consists of ballot problems, correspondence, orientation manuals, meeting materials (including conference call meetings), polls conducted by of Board, program requests, and reports to the Board. The Executive Committee subseries consists of meeting and a 1991 committee retreat materials.
  - Board of Directors
    - Ballots, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1978-85 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Manuals
      - Orientation, 1979-2006, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 3-14)
        [see also OVERSIZED]
      - Policy, 1982, 1987 update (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - Meetings
      - 1976-October 1981 (Box 6, Folder 3-13)
      - November 1981-1983 (Box 7, Folder 1-7)
      - 1984-85 (Box 8, Folder 1-8)
      - 1986 (Box 9, Folder 1-5)
      - 1987-88 (Box 10, Folder 1-7)
      - 1989-92 (Box 11, Folder 1-8)
      - 1993-96 (Box 12, Folder 1-6)
      - 1997-99 (Box 13, Folder 1-7)
      - 2000-02 (Box 14, Folder 1-9)
    - Members, 1985-88, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Outreach, 1985 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Polls
      - Fundraising, 1978 (Box 15, Folder 3)
      - Miscellaneous,1980, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Program related requests forwarded to the Board, 1984 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Reports to the Board
      - Consultants: Hartnet & Associates, 1983 (Box 15, Folder 6)
      - Financial
        [See SERIES V. FINANCIAL MATERIALS - Reports to the Board]
      - Fundraising, 1980-89
        [See SERIES V. FINANCIAL MATERIALS - Fundraising - Reports to the Board]
      - Miscellaneous, 1978-82 (Box 15, Folder 7-11)
  - Contracts and legal materials, 1980 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Executive Committee
    - Meetings (Box 15)
      - 1972-86 (Box 16, Folder 1-15)
      - 1987-90 (Box 17, Folder 1-10)
      - 1991-95 (Box 18, Folder 1-6)
      - 1996-99 (Box 19, Folder 1-9)
      - 2000-03 (Box 20, Folder 1-11)
    - Retreat, 1991 (Box 20, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous, 1979-81, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - Leases and office business, 1978-83 (Box 20, Folder 14)
- SERIES III. COMMITTEES, 1978-2004
  [See also SERIES IX. PROJECTS, PROGRAMS, AND REFORM EFFORTS]
  The committees of the NWHN fall into two general categories: administrative committees and program committees. The administrative committees include by-laws, personnel, fundraising, publications, and nominations and elections. There are also ad hoc committees and advisory committees. This series is arranged alphabetically and contains correspondence, minutes, notes, agendas and printed material on twenty-nine committees, many of which are reflected in SERIES IX. PROJECTS, PROGRAMS, AND REFORM EFFORTS. There is miscellaneous category which includes budgets, lists, correspondence, and responses to a survey: "Want to join a committee?"
  - Administrative, 1981-87, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Affiliates, 1983 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Assessment, 2004-05 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Breast cancer, 1982-93 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Cervical Cap, 1982 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Depo-Provera, 1982 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - DES (diethylstibestrol), 1982-83 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Disabilities, 1982 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Domestic Violence, 1983 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Finance, 1982 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    [See also SERIES V. FINANCIAL MATERIALS]
  - Health Law and Regulation, 1982 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Infant Formula, 1982-83 (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - International Health, 1981-82 (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - Long Range Planning, 1982-83 (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - Maternal Health and Childbirth, 1982-89 (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - Membership, 1981-82 (Box 21, Folder 16)
  - Midlife and Older Women, 1982-84 (Box 21, Folder 17)
  - National Health System, 1987 (Box 21, Folder 18)
  - Nominations and Elections, 1978-84, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 1-6)
  - Nursing Home, 1983-89 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Nutrition, 1981-84 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Occupational and Environmental Health, 1980-90 (Box 23, Folder 1-4)
  - Personnel, 1982-84 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Program Prioritization, 2001 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Public Relations and Publications, 1982-87 (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Reorganization, 1983 (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Reproductive Rights, 1981-84, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 1-3)
  - Rural Health, 1982-83 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    [see also SERIES VII. CONFERENCES AND MEETINGS - NWHN - Appalachian Pathways]
  - Sterilization, 1985 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Budgets, 1982 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Committee lists and miscellaneous correspondence, 1981-83 (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - Responses to "want to join a committee," 1981-82 (Box 24, Folder 8)
- SERIES IV. PERSONNEL AND BOARD MEMBERS, 1979-2007
  [see also SERIES III. COMMITTEES - Nominations and Elections]
  This series relates to NWHN staff, board members, interns, and volunteers. It is arranged in three subseries: Positions, Personnel, and Miscellaneous staff records. The first consists of correspondence, activity reports, job descriptions, evaluations, printed material, and a program director's notebook related to the positions of action vice chair (a position for developing issues to bring to the committees for action), administrative vice chair, development director, executive director, program director, interns, and volunteers. Interns provide support to the staff, especially with the information clearinghouse which responds to women's inquiries. There is a copy of the "Clearinghouse Journal" to which interns contributed, correspondence regarding internships, lists and biographies, two orientation manuals, and a list of projects performed by interns. There is also a folder of volunteer correspondence and information forms.
  The Personnel subseries contains correspondence, meeting notes, job descriptions, working files, and biographical materials related to program directors Amy Allina, Lisa Cox, and Toni Young; research coordinator Marina Baroof; administrative assistant Marlene Fisher; clearinghouse and intern coordinator Sonja Herbert; founder Mary Howell; Executive Directors Victoria Leonard and Cindy Pearson; membership coordinator Lisa McFadden; Board members Barbara Seamon, Sybil Shainwald, and Janet Stallmeyer; and member services coordinator June Thomas. Cindy Pearson's file contains material related to her review of Judith Houck's Hot and Bothered: Women, Medicine and Menopause in Modern America, Pearson's trip to Winston-Salem in 2003, and her "worry lists." In 1970 Barbara Seamon revealed the dangers of oral contraceptives in her book The Doctors Case Against the Pill. The bulk of the material on Barbara Seamon consists of research material for this book.
  Miscellaneous staff records consists of activity sheets, a board and leadership involvement survey, employment inquiries, leadership lists and training, personnel policies, memos, meetings, contracts, testimonies, and presentations.
  - Positions
    - Action vice-chair, 1982 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Administrative vice-chair, 1980 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Development director search, 1981 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Executive Director
      - Job description and evaluations, 198-82, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 4)
      - Reports, 1980-89 (Box 25, Folder 5)
      - Search, 1983-84, 1990 (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - Interns
      - "Clearinghouse Journal" n.d. (Box 25, Folder 7)
      - Correspondence regarding internships, 1979, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 8)
      - Eunice Corfman Internship, 1983 (Box 25, Folder 9)
      - Lists and biographies, 1986-95 (Box 25, Folder 10)
      - Orientation Manual and "All About the Network," 1982, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 11)
      - Projects, 1982 (Box 25, Folder 12)
    - Program director
      - Note book, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 13-14)
      - Reports, 1983-85, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 15)
    - Volunteers, 1982-83, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Personnel
    - Allina, Amy (program director), 2002-05 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Baroff, Marina (research coordinator), 1978-79 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Cox, Lisa (program/public policy director), 1995-96 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Fisher, Marlene (administrative assistant), 1993 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Herbert, Sonja (clearinghouse/intern coordinator), 1993, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Howell, Mary (founder), 1998 (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - Leonard, Victoria (executive director), n.d. (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - McFadden, Lisa (membership coordinator), 1996 (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - Pearson, Cindy (program director and executive director)
      - "Hot and Bothered" review, 2005 (Box 27, Folder 10)
      - Winston-Salem trip, 2003 (Box 27, Folder 11)
      - Worry Lists, 1996-2001 (Box 27, Folder 12-13)
      - Miscellaneous, 1993- 2001 (Box 27, Folder 14)
    - Seaman, Barbara (Board member), 1993-2004
      - Oral contraception, 1980-2004 (Box 27, Folder 1)
      - Miscellaneous, 1993-97 (Box 27, Folder 2-3)
    - Shainwald, Sybil (chair of the board), 1984-86 (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Stallmeyer, Janet (board member), 1988 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Thomas, June (member services coordinator), 1982-86 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Young, Toni (program director), 1993 (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous personnel records
    - Activity sheets, 1984-97 (Box 28, Folder 1-3)
    - Board and leadership involvement survey, 1981 (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - Employment inquiries, 1984-85 (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - Leadership lists, 1980-88, n.d. (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Leadership training, 2001 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Meetings, 1993-2007 (Box 28, Folder 8-14)
  - Miscellaneous personnel records (continued) (Box 28)
    - Memos (miscellaneous), 1993-2003 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Personnel policies, 1979-84 (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - Staff contracts, 1978-2000 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Testimonies and presentations by staff
      - Opportunities for Research on Women's Health, 1991 (Box 29, Folder 4)
      - Miscellaneous, 1973-97, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous, 1980-85, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 6)
- SERIES V. MEMBERSHIP AND FINANCIAL MATERIALS, 1977-2006
  This series is divided into two subseries: Membership and Financial materials. Membership materials contain information on the many ways the NWHN tried to build its membership base. Through direct mail, seasonal, and special appeals. In addition there is some miscellaneous database improvement material. Most recruitment was done via direct mail and there is a section specifically related to the direct mail process including strategies, analysis and planning, interviews, letters, and campaigns, as well as correspondence and miscellaneous materials from ten consultants that were hired between 1979 and 1995 to coordinate the direct mail campaign. There is also membership-related correspondence including letters which the Network classified as "interesting." Other membership information includes membership analysis, a membership identity project, planning strategies, and procedures for membership renewals and acquisitions. There is section specifically on renewals. In 1980 the Network sent out questionnaires to those people who did not renew their membership, generating interesting responses and renewal analysis. Finally there are membership reports to the Board, membership surveys, and telemarketing information.